{"tossups": [{"question": "A National company in this industry was founded by Henry \u201cJudge\u201d Moore. Its not in the financial industry, but a man named Charles Schwab founded a company in this industry named for Bethlehem, Pennsylvania. The largest of these companies was founded by J.P. Morgan from a company once owned by a Scottish entrepreneur who wrote \u201cThe Gospel of Wealth.\u201d For ten points, name this industry whose largest company is named \u201cU.S. [this]\u201d and was originally formed by Andrew Carnegie.", "answer": "<b> steel</b> industry", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This discipline\u2019s name was coined by a scholar in the House of Wisdom, al-Khwarizmi. For ten points, name this branch of mathematics that involves manipulating and solving equations.", "answer": "<b> algebra</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "Haci I Giray founded a state in this region that gained nominal independence in the Treaty of Kuchuk Kainarji. Alfonso La Marmora and Aimable \u00b4Pelissier fought together in a campaign in this region. A year later in this region, Pavel Liprandi\u2019s forces retreated, thinking that a large force lay behind Colin Campbell\u2019s 93rd Regiment, which had formed the \u201cthin red line.\u201d The Siege of Sevastopol was interrupted by the Battle of Balaclava in an 1850s war named for this region. For ten points, name this peninsula that juts into the Black Sea.", "answer": "<b> Crimea</b>n peninsula (or<b> Tauris</b> or<b> Tauric</b> peninsula; accept<b> Crimea</b>n Khanate; accept <b>Crimea</b>n War) Page 1", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A November 2015 book about this policy noted how it was primarily formulated by rocket engineers. This policy led to creation of a group of \u201cblack\u201d individuals who could not receive education or health care services. The \u201c4-2-1\u201d problem was created by this policy, which also led to the phenomenon of \u201clittle emperors.\u201d This policy exacerbated the use of sex-selective abortions in the country where it was enacted, leading to an excess of over 30 million males. For ten points, name this policy which limited births in China until 2015.", "answer": "<b> One Child</b> Policy", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "Upon winning a game in this sport, Vitas Gerulaitis noted that \u201cnobody beats Vitas Gerulaitis 17 times in a row!\u201d In 2016, Raymond Moore, a tournament director in this sport, resigned after saying that women in this sport \u201care very, very lucky\u201d to \u201cride on the coattails\u201d of its men. In 2007, the final major championship of this sport announced gender pay equity; that championship is held at the All-England Club. For ten points, name this sport played at Wimbledon by Serena Williams and Roger Federer.", "answer": "<b> tennis</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "During this war, Scott O\u2019Grady was rescued after being shot down while maintaining a no-fly-zone in Operation Deny Flight. One side in this war was supported by the White Eagles and Arkan\u2019s Tigers. The Heliodrom prisoner camp was set up in this war, in which Operation Storm became the largest European battle since World War II. Under the leadership of Ratko Mladic [m\u2019lah-ditch], the VRS and the Scorpions perpetrated the Srebrenica [sreh-breh-nee-tzah] massacre in this war. The Dayton Peace Accords ended, for ten points, what 1992-95 Yugoslavian war that broke out after an independent country was established at Sarajevo?", "answer": "<b> Bosnian</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler\u2019s daughter Enheduanna wrote a religious work titled<em> The Exaltation of Inanna</em>. The birth legend of this leader, who defeated king Lugal-Zage-Si of Umma, has been compared to that of Moses. This former servant of Ur-Zababa had his troops wash their weapons in the ocean to symbolize one of his conquests. This former cupbearer took control of Kish, Lagash, and Uruk to become the first emperor. For ten points, name this founder of the Akkadian Empire.", "answer": "<b> Sargon</b> the Great Page 2", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man was injured when his guard misthrew a grenade, hitting a wall and falling in front of him. That action came after this man and his son, Mutassim, crawled threw a drainage pipe to escape an attacked convoy. This man\u2019s body was showcased in a freezer in Misrata, and a cell phone video depicts people stabbing a bayonet into his rear end. This man\u2019s murder was lamented by Mahmoud Jibril, who wished to see him tried for crimes against humanity. For ten points, name this leader who was killed in October 2011 after the National Transitional Council won a civil war against this man\u2019s regime in Libya.", "answer": "Muammar<b> Gaddafi</b> (or Muammar al-<b>Qaddafi</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Harold MacMillan reacted to being snubbed by Charles de Gaulle by changing the name of this brand. Andre Turcat served as a tester for this brand. One of these vehicles suffered an accident in Gonesse that killed over one hundred people; that accident in 2000 involved a tire punctured by debris on the ground. The Tupolev Tu-144 was the only competitor to this vehicle, which stopped operations in 2003. The slogan was \u201cArrive before you leave\u201d was used by, for ten points, what defunct supersonic passenger jet service?", "answer": "<b> Concord</b>e", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "During the Spanish-American War, John Parker\u2019s use of this weapon earned him the nickname [this weapon] Parker. Henry Raymond used one of these weapons to defend<em> The New York Times</em> during the New York anti-draft riots. The creator of this weapon stated if I could \u201cenable one man to do as much battle duty as a hundred\u201d it would \u201csupersede the necessity of large armies.\u201d This weapon inspired the creation of \u201crotary cannons\u201d which include the M61 Vulcan. For ten points, name this popular Civil War weapon, named for its creator, which fired bullets as fast as a soldier could crank the handle.", "answer": "<b> Gatling</b> Gun", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Abdul ibn Baz authorized the use of deadly force in this event against his former students. Christian Proteau helped plan the response to this event, whose perpetrators were charged with \u201cmisidentifying the Mahdi.\u201d This event was carried out by members of the Ikhwan militia under Juhayman al-Otaibi, and King Khaled caved to their demands rather than crack down on extremism. The perpetrators of this event called for the overthrow of the House of Saud. For ten points, name this 1979 event that began when extremists seized the Mecca complex housing the Kaaba.", "answer": "raid of the<b> Grand Mosque</b> (accept alternatives like \u201cseizure\u201d instead of \u201craid\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these people orchestrated a coup to exile a leader to Ropsha, a manor that was then given to that person. The size of this group of people prompted the nickname \u201cMessalina on the Neva.\u201d One of these people lost this status shortly after the Kosciuszko Uprising, and another of these people legendarily built mock villages along the Dnieper River to impress a certain somebody on her visit to Crimea. For ten points, name these men, such as Grigory Orlov and Grigory Potemkin, who had an amorous relationship with a \u201cGreat\u201d empress of Russia.", "answer": "<b> lovers</b> of<b> Catherine</b> the<b> Great</b> (accept<b> Catherine II</b> for Catherine the Great; accept just Catherine after it\u2019s read; accept synonyms for lovers; prompt on any individual lover)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This goddess was the older figure honored in a festival in which married Athenian women traveled out of town for three days and worshipped Kalligeneia. Pigs were sacrificed at that summer festival, which honored this goddess and her child. This goddess\u2019s \u201cdescent,\u201d \u201csearch,\u201d and \u201cascent\u201d were the subject of the Eleusinian Mysteries, a ritual focused on this goddess\u2019s search for her daughter, who had been kidnapped by Hades. For ten points, name this mother of Persephone, the Greek goddess of the harvest.", "answer": "<b> Demeter</b>", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "<b>To deceive enemy forces into believing this group had not yet retreated, William Scurry invented a self-firing rifle that fired once cans had filled with dripping water. This group encountered fierce resistance on Lone Pine Hill on the 400 Plateau. Future historian (+) Charles Bean reported on the fighting encountered after this group made an amphibious landing at a cove now named for them. A holiday named in remembrance of this group occurs on April (*) </b> 25, during which sprigs of rosemary are worn and the Last Post is played. For ten points, name this group comprised of soldiers from two \u201cdown under\u201d British dominions, who fought bravely at Gallipoli.", "answer": "<b> A</b>ustralian and<b> N</b>ew<b> Z</b>ealand<b> A</b>rmy<b> C</b>orps", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This deity swore her husband, Shantanu, to never question her actions, then killed each of their first seven children in an attempt to protect them from a curse. A 7th century bas-relief monument on the Coromandel Coast depicts this deity landing on Shiva\u2019s hair</b> <b>during her (+)</b> <b>descent to Earth. This deity personifies a location where drops of amrita</b> <b>inspired four pilgrimage sites that are visited in a (*)</b> 12-year cycle. Millions of people undertake the Kumbh Mela, a pilgrimage to, for ten points, what sacred river into which the ashes of deceased Hindus are scattered?", "answer": "<b> Ganges</b> River (or<b> Ganga</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "</b> <b>This team\u2019s most famous work involved an awkward front porch conversation with Ronald Paquin and helped bring about the ouster of Bernard Law. An investigation led by this group\u2019s then-editor (+) Walter Robinson included stories by Michael Rezendes and resulted in over 600 stories being published about (*) </b> sexual abuse within the Catholic Church. For ten points, name this team of investigated journalists at the Boston Globe, the subjects of a namesake 2015 film.", "answer": "<b> Spotlight</b> team (prompt on Boston Globe before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This treaty was signed on the (*)</b> Neman River when two emperors met on rafts. For ten points, name this treaty that forced Russia into joining the Continental System against Great Britain.", "answer": "Treaty of<b> Tilsit</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Henry Campbell-Bannerman called these places \u201cmethods of barbarism\u201d in response to the rhetorical question \u201cWhen is a war not a war?\u201d A photo taken at one of these locations shows an emaciated Lizzie van Zyl, whose eventual death was used by Emily (+) Hobhouse to protest conditions in these places. A commission headed by Millicent Fawcett condemned these places, whose population grew dramatically after Lord (*) </b> Kitchener started using a scorched earth strategy. For ten points, name these locations used by the British to hold civilians during the Second Boer War, whose name was later used to describe similar facilities during the Holocaust.", "answer": "<b> concentration camp</b>s (or<b> internment camp</b>s; do not accept or prompt on death camps or extermination camps) Page 11", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A city of this name was taken from Gorgas by his brother Oenislus, who proceeded to assault nearby Amanthus. A statesman considered that a prophecy about this place called it \u201cmerciless,\u201d rather than \u201cdivine,\u201d and used income from Laurium to build \u201cbulwarks of</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>wood\u201d that he stored on this island. At a battle named for this location, Artemisia of</b> <b>Halicarnassus fought bravely for a king (*)</b> watching from Mt. Aigaleo; that king was disappointed, as freshly-rested men crushed his exhausted rowers, whose ships had entered a trap set by Themistocles. For ten points, give this name shared by a decisive naval defeat for Xerxes the Great in 480 BC.", "answer": "<b> Salamis</b> (accept Battle of<b> Salamis</b>) ", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This company was preceded by the South Improvement Company and was founded in Cleveland. One of this company\u2019s founders was the father of Palm Beach and Miami,</b> <b>Florida, Henry (+)</b> <b>Flagler, who pioneered this company\u2019s tactic of working with</b> <b>railroads to get shipping rebates. This company was the subject of a 19-part (*)</b>\u201chistory\u201d by an author for<em> McClure\u2019s magazine</em>, which led to this company\u2019s breakup under the Sherman Antitrust Act. For ten points, name this monopoly created by John D. Rockefeller.", "answer": "<b> Standard Oil</b> Company", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}